Never forget why you are the church.
Amen.
Go ahead and turn your Bibles to Romans chapter 12.
Romans chapter 12.
This morning, we are moving right along through this 12th
chapter of Romans, looking at how we are to biblically
respond to others.
We can say all the nice things that we want about each other, but
what do your actions reveal regarding your
relationships with others.
These commands in this portion of text speaks primarily on reactions.
Last week, we looked at the 1st one in Romans chapter
12, verse 14, it says this, the less than which
persecutes you, bless and curse not.
Let me read that again.
Bless them which persecutes you.
Bless and curse not.
Are you someone who blesses or curses?
Well, you don't know what they did or what they said or you don't
really know really what you're talking about.
I want to clarify something here.
Nowhere in scripture is sin ever
justified or tolerated.
Just because there's sin in scripture,
just because there's people of God who have sinned that
is recorded in the text does not mean that God ever justified
or tolerated that sin.
The sinner may try to do so, but God's holiness
does not and will not allow it.
So I don't want you to miss that.
That being true, what someone has done to us does
not give us the right to curse them.
Listen, just because someone's done something, doesn't mean that
what they have done to us isn't wrong.
Doesn't mean that someone has not abused this.
It doesn't mean that someone has not done a bad thing.
What I'm trying to say is our biblical reaction is
based on scripture and God's word, not our feelings.
Now, what does it look like to curse someone?
Remember the meaning, to curse, pronounce, a curse upon, refers
to the act of pronouncing misfortune for someone else.
Do you understand the depth of this command, even when someone is
directly attacking you?
And by the way, we talked at length last week about how
a lot of these things that we talk about is a direct attack
on us and, oh, preacher, I'm going through persecutions, that's not a persecution.
That's just an off day.
Persecution is leaving the house and having someone literally
because of your faith, going after you, intentionally
and nonstop.
That's what Timothy saw or that's what, sorry, Stephen saw in scripture.
That's what Jesus saw when he was here on his earth.
But it's someone making their mission to hurt you.
It's not that you don't handle business and protect yourself.
Rather, you make sure you can never be found lowering yourself
to their level.
Blessed, do not curse.
We moved this morning to the next one.
Romans 12, verse 15.
It says this.
Rejoice with them that do rejoice and weep with them.
that weep.
Last week, we looked at the power of persecution.
Why was that the title?
Well, think about it.
If you are truly getting persecuted.
And you respond with blessing and not cursing.
Let me just tell you something.
That's going to be noticed.
Everybody in the world curses those who curse them.
Everybody in the world, when someone does someone wrong, they lash
out and they say this, they say that, but man, when a believer,
even though they're getting persecuted, speaks highly of
this person, not of what they've done, but says, hey, God loves you.
I forgive you, all the things.
Man, that is noticed.
That is a testimony right in of itself.
So there's power in persecution, but also this week we're
going to look at the power of empathy.
The power of empathy.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you for this morning.
I thank you, God, for this gathering.
So Lord, allow me to preach, God, with power and clarity.
Well, God, I pray those that have ears to hear.
May they hear.
In Jesus name, pray.
Amen.
There are many issues with the church today.
But I'm not stating that as others do.
A lot of people like to beat up on the bride.
A lot of people like to beat up on the local church.
A lot of people like to get on social media and give their
opinion about why the church isn't what it needs to be and this and that,
blah, blah, blah.
I believe that the church is a beautiful and biblical thing.
I believe the church is full of broken yet restored people who
come together with the same purpose and intention of honoring God together.
Now, that's not obviously everybody.
But why let the fake ones take away from the real ones.
Amen?
Well, preacher, I think I'll just have church at my house with a select
few, and we'll just kind of do what we want to do.
Well, let me just, if your goal is discipleship, then I'm all the way in.
We would call that a small group.
Amen?
We would call bringing a few people into your home and
discipling them and teaching the Bible.
There's nothing wrong with that.
Jesus preached to the masses and he discipled a few.
That is a biblical and successful model.
However, if you do this so that you can make
the rules and everything can be on your terms.
You aren't having church.
You're doing exactly what you accuse the local church down the street of doing.
Making the rules.
Don't come to me thinking you can do better than everybody else.
It's easy to sit back and say, oh, well, I'd have done that.
I would have done this.
Well, guess what?
Something got done.
It wasn't by you.
See, even with the flaws, the local church is a force for good
that must not be taken for granted.
Now, one of these many issues that I alluded to is derived
from the principles found in verse 15, the church, I believe,
has lost its empathy.
Now, what does it mean to have empathy?
Empathy is the capacity to feel another
person's feelings, thoughts, or attitudes vicariously.
Now, empathy is not to be mistaken with sympathy.
Now, sympathy, and I'm talking about how the world sees and
how the world defines these, right?
Sympathy is having compassion and pity from
an outside perspective.
Empathy brings you inside with the person in
order to walk with them through their hurt or their joy.
I'll give you an example, and then we'll break down the 2 phrases here in verse 15.
Sympathy is seeing that same Facebook post and
messaging them with the intention of stepping or, I'm
sorry, sympathy is seeing a Facebook post and someone going through
something sad.
We see it all the time on Facebook and out of
sympathy, you click the care emoji or you
click the little heart emoji and you might even you might
even comment, oh, praying for you.
That's sympathy.
That is seeing a need and being sad from afar.
Empathy is seeing that same message, direct
message and saying, hey, listen, how can I help you?
How can I walk with you through this?
How can I, how can I be there for you?
Sympathy is thinking about someone in the hospital suffering?
Man, I can't believe they're at the hospital.
I can't believe they had to go.
They've been there for 3 or 4 days.
Empathy is going and sitting with them during their suffering.
Sympathy is actual concern, but from a distance.
Empathy is concerned, it turns into action.
If you want to write anything down, write this down.
Sympathy is feeling for, Empathy is feeling with.
Sympathy is feeling for empathy is filling with.
Everyone with me so far.
Now, Paul here starts this verse by saying, rejoice with them that do rejoice.
Now, most think that epathy is only for bad situations,
but here we see that we are to walk with others even
in their triumphs.
I'm gonna say something that may sound incorrect, but if we're honest, we know it to be true.
Let me hit you with this.
It is more difficult to celebrate with others in their good
times than to suffer with others in their bad times.
You know with me?
Let me explain that.
It is more difficult to celebrate with others in their successes
and their victories than it is when they're going through a hard time.
What could possibly cause this?
Well, pride?
Ego, jealousy, covishness, laziness.
They have what you desire, so instead of rejoicing with
them, you would rather nitpick and superficially congratulate them, and
then move on as fast as possible, not thinking about what God has blessed them with.
Someone's business grows exponentially.
Someone's family expands, the young couple builds their dream home.
Your coworker friend gets that promotion.
Listen, if you don't think that pastors deal with this, you're out of your stinking mind.
Listen, it's very easy.
Comparison is the thief of joy.
And we live in a county that has a lot of good growing churches.
And I can tell you right now, it's easy sometimes to compare,
the church down the street hits record attendance.
The church of a similar size, they able to operate with double the budget.
The church in town and seeing their programs grow and thrive and
see what the flesh wants to do.
The flesh wants to downplay it.
Ah, we'll see.
They just started it.
It won't be successful for long.
It probably won't continue.
Well, I didn't want that promotion anyway.
They are crazy to building this economy.
I want to give you 2 points to remember when it comes to rejoicing with those who rejoice.
First off, what you rejoice about reveals your heart posture.
If you can rejoice with someone, even in their victories, what you're
saying is, listen, I'm living in humility, and you'll win is a win for me.
Can I tell you something?
People say, hey, listen, I don't think people should be rich.
I don't think money's a bad thing.
I think the love of money is the root of all evil.
I think we are to use money, not money use us.
Does that make sense?
And let me just tell you something.
Somebody that makes a lot of money is very well off.
Listen, they can do things that other people may not be able to do.
That's a win.
So all I'm trying to say is we should celebrate that.
Our heart posture.
What is a second?
Fake rejoicing is easy to spot.
Have you ever fake rejoiced over something that you didn't really want to rejoice over?
It's like, oh, I'm so happy for you.
Thank you for sharing that.
I'm so glad that happened to you.
Listen, we do it all time.
You may think you are good at hiding it.
Your pride and jealousy, but you are not.
many people have this mindset.
You know the song, The Lord bless you.
Unless he blesses you more than me.
And keep you.
Make his face shine upon you.
Just not as bright as he's shining on me.
Think about it for a second.
Listen, I know it's silly, but that's how we live our life oftentimes.
It's really cool until someone gets something that we wanted.
What a meansable way to live, amen?
Now, you may be thinking that this has been a lot of opinion rather than scripture.
And, you know, hey, listen, any opinion I have, I pray
that I base it on scripture.
Amen.
So is there an example of this in the Bible?
Well, you know it is.
I wouldn't be saying this stuff.
Remember King Saul.
The 1st king of Israel.
How does scripture describe this man?
First Samuel 9, verse 2 says this.
He had a son whose name was Saul, a choice and
handsome man, and there was not a more handsome person than
he among the sons of Israel from his shoulders and up.
He was taller than any of the people.
This dude, physically, was seemingly the perfect fit for a king.
Early on, he had experienced some pretty significant wins.
He united the scattered 12 tribes.
He established the military and administrative state.
He led early Israelite forces through critical battlefield victories.
I mean, King Saul was making it happen as king.
He was on top of the world.
Nobody could beat him.
Then this young shepherd boy named David arrived.
See, David, at a young age, was no had no experience
of ruling, but he had a boldness and a courage
that Saul did not have.
David was displayed, he displayed a faith
in God that exposed Saul's lack of faith in God.
It was David who slew Goliath while Saul sat
back and allowed the enemy to blaspheme the name of God.
It was David who became known as a mighty warrior.
As a matter of fact, in 1st Samuel 18, 5 and 7.
It says this.
So David went out wherever Saul sent him.
and prospered.
That means he was successful.
And Saul set him over the men of war, and it was pleasing
in a side of all the people, and also in a side of Saul's servants,
it happened as they were coming, when David returned from killing the
Philistine, that the women came out of all the cities of
Israel singing and dancing to meet King Saul
with tambourines, with joy, and with musical instruments.
But what were they singing?
The women sang as they played and said, Saul
has slain his 1000s and David his 10 thousands.
Uh-oh.
Saul didn't take this too kindly.
He wasn't in the mood to rejoice over that.
Why are they singing about David?
It's 10,000s and only my thousands.
Look at how Saul responded in verses 8 and nine.
Then Saul became very angry.
for this saying, displeased him, and he said, they have ascribed to
David 10,000s, but to me they have ascribed thousands.
Now, what more can he have but the kingdom?
Saul looked at David with suspicion from that day on.
Now, do we understand how that song being sung in the
cities would have irritated Saul?
Of course we do.
I'm not sitting here saying that Saul had to enjoy it.
You know what I'm saying?
Like, I mean, obviously that's a pretty, pretty significant, you know, cut to him.
However, it was King Saul who set David over the minute war.
It was King Saul who sent him to the feet, the enemies of Israel.
It was King Saul that made him the fighter that he
was and gave him the opportunities.
God gave David the victory, but Saul gave him the opportunities.
King Saul, no matter the personal emotions, could have realized
that God was using David for the good of his people.
This was something to rejoice about, yet so often we let our
pride and ego get in the way.
If we aren't getting praise, we don't want anyone else to get praised.
There's been times where we've had people come
and preach, and we've even had pastors on staff and stuff,
and there's been people who come to me and they say, Jacob,
you know, he's a really good preacher, you intimidated.
Like, don't you think if you get him to come in and people
start liking him and they'll boot you out and they'll bring him in?
And my answer has always been, so be it, baby.
Just kidding.
I do like to be here.
That was a joke for the...
So serious this morning.
But listen, seriously, listen, I don't have to be intimidated by that.
Because I know what God has called me to.
And see, see, when God calls you to something.
That is the strength that you need for any other somethings to come about in your life.
And so we have to understand that even in King Saul's
example here, we're looking at, he sent him out.
He gave the opportunity.
Listen, if he's slain thousands,
and David's slain 10,000s.
understand, that means that 10s of 1000s of the enemies
of Israel were being defeated.
This is a win for the kingdom for God's people.
It's kind of like getting mad when another church has a revival
or a conference and they get 20 people saved
and 20 people make a decision to follow Christ and we're like, oh,
well, they just, you know, their invitation is like this and this is that.
No, praise the Lord.
20 people are going to heaven.
We should celebrate that.
We're starting the Iwana program and let's
say a church down the street starts another one of program.
And we have 30 kids in hours and they have 50 kids in hours.
Guess what?
Praise the Lord.
There's a ton of kids in a marijuana program.
Can I tell you something?
We tell people all the time this.
You do realize that 80% of Wilson County are unchurched.
80% of Wilson County, one of the fastest growing counties.
80% of them are at home right now.
And yet we got these churches fighting over all these territory wars.
Let's just go out and get them.
And if another church gets them, let's praise the Lord for that.
Let's get the next one.
You understand what I'm saying?
Listen, it's not just the church structure.
That's how we ought to live our life with others as well.
People go obedience calls for us to step into the celebration of other successes and victories.
When someone succeeds, how do you respond?
Romans 12, 15.
Rejoice with them that they rejoice.
But that's just half of it.
We also see in the same verse, rejoice with them that
do rejoice, and weep with them that weep.
Now, here's where we could understand more the concept of empathy.
Remember the definition of empathy, right?
Empathy is the capacity to feel another person's feelings, thoughts,
or attitudes vicariously.
You're putting yourself in the situation.
You're walking with them in their pain.
Because of the society we live in, this is typically reduced to an outside feeling
of sympathy rather than an intentional joining of carrying a burden.
And I see this work both ways in our culture, by the way.
I want you to pay attention here.
People love to talk about walking through the valley with someone
until the time comes to actually start walking.
You know, if you're not from the south, right?
I know we got some people that are not from the south.
Anyone ever heard of southern hospitality, we've talked about this a whole bunch.
Southern hospitality is this.
Man, we should get together.
Buddy?
Well, that sounds like I'm just calling you buddy.
your real name.
Buddy, we should get together, man.
So you know why?
Because, man, I like you.
I'm glad God put you in my life.
Let's get together.
Let's fellowship, all right?
Five years later.
Buddy, let's get together sometime, man.
I just like, that's how, that's southern hospitality.
Right?
We have all the intentions in the world of getting together and living life
together and being friends and serving the Lord together,
but yet for some reason, we just live our own separate lives,
and those intentions make us feel like we're good people,
and we're doing the right things, but in reality, we're just living for ourselves.
Y'all with me?
Why does it take intentionality to be relational with other believers?
You know why?
Because it takes you taking yourself out of your schedule to help somebody else.
Again, but I see this work in both ways, right?
All of a sudden, we don't have time or bandwidth or the capacity to help anymore.
Can I tell y'all something this morning?
Sending a text that says, if you need anything, let me know with
no intentions of helping with anything.
It's not empathy.
it's lying.
And you know the text I'm talking about.
Oh, praying for you, brother sister.
If you need anything, let me know.
Please don't let me.
But that's how that's how we live.
You never bother me unless you bother me.
Is this is hard for you to hear as it is for me?
Y'all sit understand at me like I done, kicked your puppy or something.
I'm not a puppet kicker.
Once it bites me, then I kick it.
Ah, have a story.
I've already told this story, and not about kicking a puppy.
Hold on, hold on.
Let me take a step back real quick.
I've never kicked a puppy on purpose.
I'm just kidding.
We were going and we were going door to door.
I probably already told a story.
We were going door to door, me and Billy, um, and we, uh, We
we went down this long windy driveway.
And it was scary.
I said no trespassing, but we thought, We're here for Jesus.
Signs don't stop the gospel.
And so we go we go down.
I mean, it's pretty sketchy.
And just the driveway.
Like, the home was nice, but it was just, you know, we're going through the woods down its driveway.
And luckily, I knew the people from Ker
Oakland, so, like, it was like, oh, thank goodness, I know them.
like, hey,
Hey, how you doing?
Hey, Pastor Jake Wall stuff.
And I'm like, hey, we're just here so we can pray for you.
Right?
Because they already told us they went to another church, so we're not sheep stealing, right?
So we'll just, hey, cool, then we'll pray for you.
And I said, what can we pray for you about, right?
And in these situations, I need you to understand something before it gets going.
You think the most spiritual person in those situations is the pastor?
But if Billy Anderson is in any of these situations,
He gets, he becomes the most spiritual person you ever see in your life.
I mean, he has his hand raised, he's bringing down the wind and the fire.
I mean, it's like insane.
I'm like, dude, chill out.
you know what I'm saying?
But anyway.
So she said, yeah, you can pray for me.
Can you pray for my cat?
Now listen.
Everyone has their personalities.
I'm not saying it's right or wrong, but I just, I'm not that kind of person.
I don't even know what it means to pray for a cat.
Well, we praying for.
I don't understand.
Is it sick?
Where is it?
So I'm sitting here and I'm like, mmm.
And so I literally, I say, I say, we absolutely will.
Billy, pray for this cat.
Billy gets down on his knees and I'm just kidding.
So, what happens is this, though?
I'm telling you what.
And this is why I don't pray for no cats no more.
We were praying for this sick cat.
Billy was praying for this sick cat.
Well, I'm praying for the home and the family, you know.
And this sick cat.
comes up out of the bushes.
Didn't look so sick to me.
Jumps upon my body.
Billy, am I lying?
He's he's saying no.
Jumps upon my body.
Okay, listen, I got a little pudge right here.
It's perfect for gripping with claws.
into my flesh.
And I'm sitting here like, oh, oh.
And I'm like, it's doing this.
I'm like, get up.
So this is what's about to happen.
Billy praying for this cat is supposedly sick.
And I'm like...
Oh.
Why did I tell that story?
I'll tell you why I told that story.
Y'all were getting too serious on me.
But listen.
I really don't know how I told that story.
Pray for people, amen?
I did not hit the cat, but in my mind, I was, I was,
I couldn't, because we're praying for it.
was sick.
All right, let's get back to it.
But it works both ways.
We will complain and state that we live in a world where no one cares or helps for us, right?
We live in this world where we think, man, I'm just isolated, and people
say they care, but they don't really care, and I've
just been hurt over and over and over again, and all the things.
But here's the issue.
We don't ask for help.
And when help is offered, we don't receive it.
We do not give the opportunity for someone to weep with us because we're too proud
to tell them why we're weeping.
Do you not think this is where the enemy wants the church?
isolated alone, suffering,
We can't help suffering in this lost world, but we can help how we do it.
All talk and no walk, all intentions and no actions.
Now I will tell you that in God's word, the term sympathy means compassion.
So when I when I compare empathy with sympathy,
I'm doing so from a worldly definition.
And it's because most people live out of this kind of definition rather
than the biblical definition, but again, you say, preacher, this sounds like a lot of opinion.
Okay, what does it mean to weep when someone's weeping?
Well, remember last week we were able to have a example
of Stephen, an example of Christ.
You do realize that if we just look to Christ, a lot of our answers will be or
questions will be answered, amen?
I want to emphasize the heart and action of Jesus.
When Jesus was told that his friend Lazarus died, what did he do?
Think about it.
When we see Martha meeting Jesus and telling him that if
he would have just been here, her brother would not have died.
Could you imagine the pain?
He was feeling.
John 11, 31 through 35 says this, then the Jews who
were with her in the house and consoling her.
When they saw that Mary got up and quickly, quickly
went out, they followed her, supposing that she was going to the tomb to weep there.
Therefore, when Mary came where Jesus was, she
saw him and fell at his feet, saying to him, Lord, if you had been here,
sorry, it was Mary, not Martha.
If you had been here, my brother would have not died.
When Jesus therefore saw her weeping.
And the Jews who came with her also weeping.
He was deeply moved in spirit and was troubled.
And said, where have you laid him?
They said to him, Lord, come and see.
And the shortest verse in the scripture, verse 35, Jesus wept.
We look at Jesus as this person who was on earth and
just this rock star of a person just
never Jesus had emotions just like we have.
Jesus had family just like we have.
He had brothers, sisters, a mom and a dad.
He had friends.
He had a job.
He had a hometown.
The shortest verse in the entire Bible reveals much about the character,
love and compassion of Christ.
He was not worried about Lazarus.
He knew Lazarus was good to go, but his heart broke for his loved ones.
If Jesus were for the hurt of others, so ought we.
We see another time in scripture where Jesus had a decompassion
for people in Matthew 9, verse 35 and 36.
Jesus was going through all the cities and villages teaching in their synagogues
and proclaiming the gospel of the kingdom and healing every kind of
disease and every kind of sickness, seeing the people.
Look what it says.
He felt compassion for them, because they were distressed
and dispirited, like a sheep, without a shepherd.
That word compassion here means to have a pity,
a deep empathy, expresses having deep compassion.
This verb is similar to what is expressed in modern language, as
feeling one's gut or heart, of deep empathy
for another person.
One may say to this, well, if all Jesus had was a feeling,
then how is that any different than someone caring but not doing anything?
Church?
He saw their need for a shepherd.
He was the good shepherd.
He saw their need for guidance, and he saw
them, he went to Calvary.
He went to the bloody cross so that he could save
the same people he was seeing in Matthew chapter 9.
The awesome part of this is that he did so, yet he was without sin.
God calls us into the fold of the same mission.
Matthew 9, 37 through 38.
Then he said to the disciples, the harvest is plentiful, but the workers a
few, therefore beseech the Lord of the harvest to send out workers into
his harvest.
Listen, I don't care how long you've been in ministry.
If a lost soul does not break your heart.
You need a fresh touch from the Lord.
I don't care how long you're in ministry.
If people's suffering does not break your heart.
You need a fresh touch from the Lord.
I have the unfortunate privilege and honor to do a funeral tomorrow.
And it's a lady that used to come to this church for a little bit
and, and, and, you know, we've known, my family's
known her and Heather's family's known her forever and ever.
And she passed away.
It was kind of all of a sudden.
And people say, man, because I've done a lot of funerals.
I mean, a lot of funerals.
I've done a lot of graveside services.
And sometimes you know the person, sometimes you don't.
And so sometimes I feel myself not getting emotional.
And I'm thinking, man, how can I stand here as the pastor?
and preach the gospel to a broken people without feeling with them.
But there's one part.
Every single time, no matter what, of the funeral that gets me.
I dont care if I know them or not.
And if you've been at a funeral, you know what I'm talking about.
It's the last viewing.
And so if they do have an open casket, what happens is, is
I come down from the pulpit and I'll stand by the casket.
And I'll stand there and the family comes in.
And they say the last goodbyes.
And I can tell you right now, I don't care who it's for.
It breaks me every time.
Church, I don't wanna lose that.
I don't want to do this for so long.
I don't want to make this such a thing to where I can't feel with people.
The Bible may not use the word empathy, but the principles throughout the scripture are clear.
First Peter 38, finally, be ye all of one mind,
having compassion, one of another.
Love as brethren, be pitiful, be courteous.
Galatians 6, verse 2, bear one another's burdens and
thereby fulfill the law of Christ.
1 Corinthians 12, 26.
And if one member suffers, all the members suffer with it.
If one member is honored, all the members rejoice with it.
Church, do you see the expectation?
God gives us 12, Romans 12, verse 15, rejoice within it,
they rejoice, and weep with them that weep.
So I have a question for you this morning.
How do you respond to the successes and victories of others?
You can't fake it.
That's your heart posture.
Secondly, Are
you willing to walk with someone in their worst day?
And on the flip side of that, Are you willing to allow
someone to walk with you on your worst day?
Listen to me, church.
We don't have to do this alone.
We're commanded.
to do this together.
But hezbanos close all of this place.